Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 1 -- Letters to Franklin 1730-1776 Mss.B.F85inventory01
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Smith, Joseph. Burlington N.J
    Present Assembly met the previous month at Amboy; understands they have continued Franklin as Agent; has received for his use £275, being two years and nine months salary as agent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 7; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jesser, -----. College Hill
    Governors of the London Hospital will be much obliged to Dr. Franklin if he will write to Mr. Colden and Mr. Dixon what he thinks to be necessary on the state of the case which Mr. Jesser left for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Returned from the country, to find the manuscript of the translation of Franklin's works by M. Lesqui, awaiting him; will not quit the work now until he has finished it. Difficulties in the way of publishing his "Petit Code de l'HumanitC)"; if the same obstacles exist in England will have it printed secretly at Caen. Has sent him the new volume of the "Ephemerides du Citoyen." Mlle. BihC)ron is occupied with Mrs. Stevenson's commission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1772.] October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Morellet, AbbC). Whycomb
    Acknowledging the letters sent him for Birmingham; expects to go to Oxford first; will make every effort to meet Franklin in Birmingham. Message to Dr. Pringle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Encloses bills of credit for £500, last year's salary as Agent for the Province. Is again elected to the Assembly. Recent changes in political conditions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, William. Philadelphia
    Failed to receive his favor of August 3d; suspects the same person who broke open his letters to his father has kept this one; question of who it can be; reasons against suspecting Lord Hillsborough; thinks it may be Wharton. Question of the Virginia grants. Has just heard that Gov. Spry of Barbadoes is dead, and that Capt. Williams, the engineer, has just taken his passage for England in hopes of being appointed Captain of Needham's Fort. Wishes he could be appointed Governor in Spry's place; is now the oldest governor in America; knows he stands no chance of promotion or increase of salary, while Lord H. is at the head of the American Department and while he is so displeased with Franklin. Desires his father to send him a handsome tea-urn: cannot afford a silver one. Has dined with Gov. Penn, with whom he has become very sociable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Death of his brother. Henry's unfaithfulness; thought best not to bind him as apprentice until he heard from Franklin. Fears he intends to break through his intention of visiting Boston every ten years.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Hutton, James
    Concerning a great work [Monde Primitif] by a friend of his [Antoine Court de GC)belin]; longs to see it finished; Franklin and Dr. Moreton the first in England to give him encouragement; he is charmed to hear that an Englishman, Mr. Bryant, is prosecuting the same work in England. Bishop of Vilna has left for Poland by way of Vienna, his great family estates being in that part which voracious Austria has seized. Marquis de Pezay just returned from his tour; Lord Lyttleton, whom he visited twice, was much pleased with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Hard at work revising the translation of Franklin's works; difficulties he encounters; asks the meaning of "orreries," "surf," "spray," "jostled." Various questions relating to his experiments. Advisability of sending him some sheets of the translation before proceeding further; concerning some new engravings for the work. Mlle. BihC)ron's intention to go to London about the end of November; her health not good and fears her expenses will be heavy; begs Franklin to let him know if this voyage promises as little success as the last; if so, he will insist on her remaining in France for the sake of her health.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 October 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, William. Burlington
    Acknowledging letters of various dates from August 3d to September 3d. Concerning the Virginia grants; begs his father to pay no heed to what Mr. Wharton may say, but to give it his particular attention; should the extent of country claimed by Virginia as its boundary be confirmed, the small tract remaining for the Proprietors of the new colony, will not be worth the purchase money; encloses letters respecting Mr. Penn's western boundary, which if true, will be most advantageous to the Proprietors of the new colony.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 November 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Westerholt, Frederik Borchard Lodewijk van. Hacforth
    In the second volume of the "Ephemerides du Citoyen" read Franklin's plan for benefiting distant unprovided countries, and was filled with admiration of such universal benevolence; though he has not the advantage of being an Englishman, hopes he may have the honor of contributing to such a laudable design the sum of four Holland ducats; is but a poor gentleman, burdened with a large family of children, but trusts Franklin will not scorn his small contribution.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 November 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Falconer, Capt Nathaniel. Philadelphia
    Has sent him one barrel of Newtown pippins, one cask of shell-bark hickory nuts and two kegs of bread. Has concluded to stay at home this year, so must forego the pleasure of keeping Christmas with Franklin. Concerning a grant of land which he asked Franklin to see Mr. Wharton about.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 November 17; L.S. 1p.; Abel James and Benjamin Morgan. Philadelphia
    The newly elected Managers of the Filature have requested them (the undersigned) to forward Capt. Lutton's bill of loading for two trunks of silk, the produce of this year, with a certificate from their Custom-house to recover bounty; also, to beg Franklin's acceptance of four pounds of the silk sent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 November 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Joseph and William Danton, Aaron Lopez, Samuel Fowler. Newport
    Recommending Capt. Richard Grinnell, of Newport, as qualified to command any vessel in the merchant service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 November 28; A.L. 4p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Is about half finished with his translation of Franklin's works in quarto. Is very anxious to receive some copies of the second edition of his little Code printed in London. In order to avoid paying excessive charges for postage, gives Franklin directions how to send the packages. Tells how he translated one passage in Franklin's works about silk worms. Sends his magic square of 11,000 numbers. Has verified Franklin's magic square of 16 and found but two mistakes in it.
    (Mutilated.) (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 November 28; A.L. in 3d P. 3p.; Henly, William
    Description and use of a new conductor for experiments in electricity contrived by Mr. Henly and executed by Mr. Edward Nairne.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1772.] ? December 6; L. 1p.; Pringle, Sir John
    Inviting him to dine, to meet Mlle. BihC)ron and Dr. Ingen Housz, before his departure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 December 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Walker, Hannah. Westbury
    Thanking him for his present. Sorry to hear of Mr. William's death; and the consequent removal of her son; begs Franklin to direct her letters [under his frank] to him, as he may now have nothing with which to pay for them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772 December 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Settlement of his accounts for the year very satisfactory; can pay all his debts and have clear profits left. His affairs with Mr. Warren.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, D. 4p.; C-----, J-----
    Reasons for establishing a colony at the Illinois. (Incomplete.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 4p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Question of colds and their causes. Effect of white walls in the cultivation of fruit. Acknowledging his letter of December 30th containing an explanation of the word chain. M. Dalibard's electrical experiments. Anxiety felt on account of Mlle. BihC)ron's state of health.
    (In French. Mutilated.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1772?; L. 8p.; Fothergill, Dr. John. London
    Political and moral reflections.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1772] Tuesday; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lettsom, John Coakley. London
    Begging Franklin's acceptance of a French hare.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1772.]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Maseres, Baron Francis
    Sending him two more copies of the collection of Quebec instruments, and the draft of a toleration act; desires one set sent to Governor Franklin, of New Jersey, and the other to Mr. Galloway, of Philadelphia. Begs for another copy of his tract called Squire Richard.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1772?] Thursday evening; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Rogers, Major Robert. London
    Informing Dr. Franklin that his petition for a tour through the North American continent comes on before the Committee of Council of Tuesday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1772.] Friday; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Ronayne, Thomas
    At Mr. Henly's instance, writes for his paper on the effects of lightning on the Tabernacle1 in order to render it more correct for publication.
    1Philosophical Transactions, LXII, 131.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1772; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Shipley, Jonathan
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 January 4; A.L.S. 3p.; O'Gorman, Thomas, chevalier
    Asks pardon for his delay in acknowledging Franklin's many civilities to him while in London. Has been busy preparing his eldest son to be a page to the King, and nursing the other two boys through the smallpox. Has had a good vintage this season, and has marked a hogs-head of his best burgundy to be sent to Franklin. Their friend Mr. Huske expects soon to return to London. Asks Franklin to write and 'hint to him with caution' their friends' thoughts upon a certain subject they have talked of.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 January 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William. Burlington
    Acknowledging his letters by the October and November packets; the former carne opened; suspects now that the villainy is on this side the water; suggests a different scal and handwriting. Glad to find that Lord D[artmouth?] has spoken so favorably of him; has written to him concerning an increase in the salary of Mr. Skinner, the Attorney General, and took that occasion to say a word in his own behalf; asks his father's influence in this matter. Encloses a copy of a letter from Lord Stirling a propos of the Virginia grants.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 January 5; A.L.S. John Hoskins et al. 2p.; The Trustees of the Burlington Free School. Burlington
    His assistance asked in presenting a petition to the King. The application of Lord Rochford for a grant of the islands in the Delaware, although thrown aside, makes the petition necessary at the present time. The income from the rents of the island supports from 25 to 30 poor children in the Free School. Hope that this income will not have to be used in obtaining a confirmation of the title. Suggest that an instruction to the Governor to grant a patent would incur the least expense. Have no private interests to promote.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 January 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Colden, Alexander. General Post-Office New York
    Enclosing certain bills of exchange; will send by next packet the printed papers, containing the advertisement about Mrs. Elizabeth Holland, and his proceedings thereon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 January 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Nobel Wimberly. Savannah
    Has not yet seen Mr. Bryan, but when he does, will take care that Franklin's and Mr. Ellis' request is fulfilled. The present Assembly has elected him Speaker, a proceeding which gave him real pleasure, but must have galled certain arbitrary men; determined, however, owing to private business, to decline accepting it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 January 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Met several gentlemen while in Jamaica who had a smattering of electricity and were great admirers of Franklin's publications on that and other philosophical subjects; never heard any report there of a building with two conductors being struck by lightning; will ask his friend Mr. Grant of Kingston to make inquiries. Fears he will have to sue Sheets' estate for the amount of Franklin's note. Concerning the expiration of the insurance on Franklin's two houses in Market Street. Mr. Hall's death much lamented. Hopes to hear soon of the completion of the Ohio grant.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 February 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Bedford, Jenny. Woodbridge N.J
    Concerning her father's (James Parker's ) affairs; his estate only encumbered with those bonds to Mr. Franklin, which they wish could be discharged, as the interest is daily accumulating. Writes on her mother's behalf, who is old and afflicted and would willingly Iive in peace. Consults him about other accounts left by her father.
    Printed in Proc. Mass. Hist. Soc., 2d Ser., XVI, p. 228.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 February 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Concerning the proposal made by Hale's friend for the payment of the debt. Disposition of certain moneys desired by Mrs. Mecom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 February 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Saussure, Horace-Bénédict de. Naples
    Conductors of lightning. Project of the Royal Society to ascertain the attration of mountains. Volcanic eruptions. Experiments on the torpedo.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 371).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 February 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Work of printing the translation goes steadily on; asks some questions concerning experiments in electricity; desires to know what Franklin considers the simplest and best among the different electrical machines. Concerning the best manner of forwarding to him one or more sheets at a time of Franklin's new edition, as well as the pamphlet of M. Dupont, who sends him a thousand compliments, as does the Marquis de Mirabeau and M. Dalibard.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 March 4; A.L. 4p.; Winthrop, Prof John. Cambridge, New England
    Returns thanks for Dr. Priestley's article on the impregnation of water with fixed air; very important discovery. Dr. Priestley's excellent character. Memorandum relating to lightning bells with report of observations of their behavior during thunder storms. Account of the damage done in a cornfield by lightning during a thunder storm on July 2, 1768. Requests Dr. Franklin to ascertain all the circumstances relative to the security of persons in an open field during a thunder storm. Thanks the Rev. Dr. Price for sending him papers on aberration, and sees clearly the source of the fallacy.
    Printed, for the most part, in Works (Sparks, VI, 375).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 March 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Lord Dartmouth. Measures adpoted by the towns in Massachusetts. Conduct of the Governor. Administration in England universally disapproved.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 36).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 6; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Todd, Anthony. General Post-Office London
    Understands that Franklin has received his accounts by that day's mail; would be glad if the Accountant-General could have them to examine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Deborah. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging his favor of January 6th. Intended to say something about Benjamin Franklin Bache, but Billy told her he had written to Franklin about him; all their children in town.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques.
    Concerning the Leyden experiment. Has a specimen of the phytolacca; believes it to be poke-weed; there are at least three kinds; which is the best? He and a friend have agreed to translate the Transactions of the American Philosophical Society. Thanks Franklin warmly for all his kindness in having his "Petit Code" printed; expresses satisfaction with the result. Could not Franklin bring Mlle. BihC)ron back with him? Sends kindest remembrances to Mrs. Hewson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Henly, William. London
    Relative to the new prime conductor (see page 128, LVIII, 29). Also to proceedings at a meeting of the Royal Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 19; A.L. 4p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Thanks for having been elected a member of the American Philosophical Society. Appreciates the honor. Discusses at length electricity and Franklin's work on the subject. His idea about lightning rods and how they should be made. His brother [Pierre] has been awarded a prize by the Academy for his calculation of longitude.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    News of Franklin's family in Philadelphia. Concerning his own and his father's business; hears that the East India Co. are to be allowed to send two ships directly to America; obliged if Franklin would recommend them to his father and himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 22; A.L.S 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter from Henry [Walker?].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Hunter, James. Philadelphia
    According to instructions, drew upon him for the sum mentioned; disposition he has made of the bill. In his low sphere of life has not the power to make Franklin any restitution, but wishes him all happiness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Wister, Daniel. Philadelphia
    Having incurred debts in his business amounting to £30,000, has been a prisoner in his own house for nearly three years; impossible in his present situation to make any attempts toward paying the debts; begs Franklin to intercede for him with his creditors in London, a list of whom he encloses; wants them to give him a letter of license for a certain number of years that he may have a chance to pay every man his due.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 April 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William. Philadelphia
    Surprised to find nothing in his favor of March 15th about the Ohio grant, as the Whartons are quite elated with the glad tidings they have received from Mr. S[amuel] Wharton. Absurd behavior of old Wharton in sending one of his sons to ask him to sell his share of the land on the Ohia. Extraordinary conduct of Lord Dunmore in granting land on the Kanawa, after what he told Lord Stirling. Has small hopes of Dr. [Cadwalader] Evans' recovery. Thought he had satisfied Haynes of there being no such estate as the one he came in search of.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 May 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Rush, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Dr. Priestley's experiment with fixed air; his observations thereon. Sending Franklin a pamphlet of his against the importation of negro slaves into Pennsylvania. Desires to see Franklin's treatise on colds; Dr. Cullen's observations on catarrhs and colds. Marriage of Rev. Mr. Coombe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1773?] May 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Blunt, Dorothea (Dolly). London
    Begging him to dine that day at Sir Charles Blunt's to meet Dr. Hawkesworth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 May 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Morgan, George. Philadelphia
    Asking Franklin to converse with Mr. Wharton on the subject of the enclosed letter, and serve Mr. Baynton's family therein.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 May 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Has received a letter from Mrs. Walker expressing great uneasiness as to the welfare of her son; has endeavored to remove it by the enclosed answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 May 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Mecom, Jenny. Boston
    Expressing great affection for Franklin, and the keenest gratitude for his generous present to her; the ardent wish of her life to be a credit to her Uncle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 May 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Falconer, Capt Nathaniel. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging his favor of February 4th. Concerning a certain claim to which he has sold his right; if Franklin has paid any money prior to the receipt of this, they are to repay it before the deed is made out.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Garrigues, Rebecca. Philadelphia
    Offering thanks for the silk which came safely to hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1773?] May 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Blunt, Dorothea (Dolly). London
    Desiring permission to have the piano forte, lent him by Franklin, removed to Streadham, where he spends more time and sees more company.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 May (?); A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William. Burlington
    Relative to [Josiah Franklin] Davenport and his desire to do something to aid him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 June 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Colden, Alexander. New York
    Wrote Franklin the 5th ult. and sent him the Office accounts and sundry bills of exchange; encloses a second set.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 June 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Mores, Edward Rowe. Leyton, Essex
    Mrs. James is so teasing that he is obliged to apply to Franklin for relief. Concerning the business of the foundry; his plan to induce Her Majesty of Russia to purchase the foundry; wishes this design kept secret; Mrs. James angry at his reticence; begs Franklin to assure Mrs. James that he knows the design and approves of it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 June 14; A.L. 2p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Concerning the letters from Governor Hutchinson and the proceedings thereon in the House.
    (Closing lines missing.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 49; Bigelow, V, 148; Smyth, VI, 57).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 June 16; A.L. 4p.; Cushing, Thomas. Province of Massachusetts Bay
    Containing the Resolves of the House of Representatives relative to the Hutchinson letters.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IV, 426).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 June 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Biheron, Marie Catherine. Paris
    Delivered to M. Dubourg the papers concerning the translations of Franklin's works. Various messages from Franklin's French friends, and to her English friends. Account of her journey to Paris. M. Dalibard enchanted with the acquisition which Franklin sent him. Recommends to Mr. Hewson's kindness a young surgeon, who goes to London to study. Warns Franklin against Mlle. Guion de St. Marie; she is little known in Paris and is said to have deceived "le pC(re Bertier."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 June 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Franklin's letter delivered to the Speaker. Encloses Gazette with the Resolves and Proceedings of their Council relative to the Governor's conduct. Commissions Franklin to get him a hand-organ like the one he had made for Mrs. Foxcroft.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 June 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning his account with Mr. Warren. Books desired by his father. Obliged to Franklin for delivering his letter to Mrs. Barwell; messages to her and other friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777 Apr. March 15]; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Will carry out Franklin's wishes as regards the transaction. Question of the mortality in certain hospitals owing to impure air.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 July 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Colden, Alexander. New York
    Enclosing several bills of exchange. His father [Cadwallader Colden] in a surprising state of health and glow of spirits.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 July 20; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Daubenton, Edmé-Louis.